<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" ".//reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<!-- WK: Set category, IPR, docName -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-wkumari-owe-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes"?>

  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <!-- WK: Set long title. -->

    <title abbrev="draft-wkumari-owe">OWE: Opportunistic Wireless
    Encryption</title>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="6" month="August" year="2015"/>

    <area>template</area>

    <workgroup>template</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a method to incrementally increase the
      security of wireless networks against passive attackers / pervasive
      monitors through unauthenticated encryption.</t>

      <t>[ Ed note: Text inside square brackets ([]) is additional background
      information, answers to frequently asked questions, general musings,
      etc. They will be removed before publication.]</t>

      <t>[ This document is being collaborated on in Github at:
      https://github.com/wkumari/draft-wkumari-owe. The most recent version of
      the document, open issues, etc should all be available here. The authors
      (gratefully) accept pull requests. ]</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="tl;dr / Executive summary">
      <t>This (colloquial) summary will be removed before publication:</t>

      <t>Currently, there are many open/unencrypted public WiFi networks,
      designed for "ease of use" in places such as coffee shops, libraries,
      etc. When a user connects to these open networks, they are using an
      unencrypted connection and their traffic can be trivially viewed by any
      other user within wireless range, simply by using a networks sniffing
      tool such as Wireshark.</t>

      <t>While users *should* use a VPN, many do not. Places that provide
      public WiFi access *should* only provide an encrypted SSID, and print
      the passphrase on the wall or receipts (or similar), but, well, they are
      a coffee shop, and want to provide easy access to everyone who buys an
      espresso...</t>

      <t>This document defines a new, opportunistically encrypted mode for
      WiFi networks. The SSID will still appear to be open (there will not be
      a "lock" icon when scanning), but will actually be encrypted, using the
      SSID as the passphrase. Software running on the client will detect that
      this is an opportunistically encrypted connection and will automagically
      provide the SSID as the passphrase, providing an encrypted connection
      without any interaction from the user. This system leverages existing
      WiFi protocols and WPA2, the only change is in operational practices and
      the client UI.</t>

      <section title="FAQ / Common questions / Notes">
        <t>Q1: If everyone uses the SSID as the key, can't attackers just use
        this to decrypt all the data?<vspace/> A: WPA2 using PSK generates a
        unique Pairwise Transient Key (PTK) between the AP and each client.
        This PTK is derived using something called the 4-Way Handshake ( see
        IEEE 802.11-2012 (or the summary at
        https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IEEE_802.11i-2004#The_four-way_handshake
        )), which includes nonces from both the client and the AP.
        Unfortunaty, this doesn't use a public key exchange (like DH), and so
        an attacker who can watch the initial clinet association can derive
        the user's encryption key. This is a weakness in WPA2-PSK, and not
        specific to OWE.</t>

        <t>Q2: So does this actually help?<vspace blankLines="0"/>A: Yes. This
        protection if the passive attacker wasn't already present when the
        user connected, or who was not able to hear both sides of the
        connection. OWE does not provide very strong protection, and does not
        claim to -- it does however raise the bar for the attacker, or force
        him to become active (and force users to disassociate (so he can watch
        the 4 way handshake)). OWE specifically does NOT provide the "lock"
        icon (or any other obvious feedback) when users scan for open wireless
        networks, because we do not want users to assume that they are getting
        "real" encryption. OWE will become more secure if and when WiFi with a
        secure PAKE / public key exchange is deployed. The incremental cost to
        implment OWE is very small (it involved adding a flag to beacons, and
        clients to know to not display the lock icon) and so we feel that the
        benfit ourweighs the cost.</t>

        <t>Q3: Isn't this vulnerable to the fake AP attack?!<vspace
        blankLines="0"/>A: Yes. An attacker can stand up their own AP with the
        same SSID and passphrase. This is true for any network that uses
        WPA2-PSK when the attacker knows the passphrase (for example, if the
        coffeeshop prints the passphrase on the wall, receipts, etc) and it
        not specific to OWE. OWE is not designed to defeat active attackers,
        nor solve all issues. See Q2.</t>

        <t>Q4: This isn't really opportunistic encryption... <vspace
        blankLines="0"/>A: Perhaps not, but it is has many of the same
        properties - it is unauthenticated, is mainly designed to deal with
        passive listeners, doesn't require interaction from the user, etc. I
        also wanted to have a cool acronym - actually I wanted it to be OWL,
        but was not able to reverse engineer a non-contrived name that made
        that...</t>

        <t>Q5: Doesn't this belong in [ IEEE | WiFi Alliance | &lt;insert
        other SDO here&gt; ] ? <vspace blankLines="0"/>A: Answer unclear, ask
        again later. I have discussed this with a number of people who
        participate in other SDOs, and it seems like the IETF is the best home
        for it, at least for now. It does not require changes to any
        underlying transport, it does not change any standards, it simply
        takes advantage of work done in other standards bodies.</t>

        <t/>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Introduction / Background">
      <t>As of time of this writing it is very common for users to connect to
      so called "open" wireless networks, for example in coffee shops, hotels,
      airports and similar. These networks provide no encryption, which means
      that the user's traffic is visible to anyone nearby with packet capture
      software, for example, Wireshark. It is also trivial for an attacker to
      perform a Man-in-the-middle attacks as they can see all of the user's
      traffic.</t>

      <t>There are a number of solutions to this problem, such as WPA2 (Wi-Fi
      Protected Access II), but these require either obtaining a passphrase
      from the network operator (WPA-Personal / Pre-Shared Key (PSK) mode) or
      having valid credentials for the network (WPA-Enterprise /
      WPA-802.1X).</t>

      <t>While these provide good security, for convenience reasons network
      operators often deploy open / unencrypted networks for public or "guest"
      use. This allows the public or visitors to get Internet access without
      having to ask for a passphrase, look around for one printed on a receipt
      or similar. Instead of chastising network operators for providing
      insecure access, this document provides a method to implement
      unauthenticated, encrypted network access.</t>

      <section title="Requirements notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="OWE protected networks">
      <t>In order to provide an encrypted connection using OWE, the network
      operator creates an SSID with the (WPA2 / 802.11i <xref
      target="IEEE.802-11i"/>) pre-shared key identical to the SSID. As part
      of the WPA2 protocol the wireless client (STAtion) and Access Point (AP)
      derive a Pairwise Transient Key (PTK), which provides an encrypted
      "channel" between the client and AP.</t>

      <section title="OWE Support Advertisement.">
        <t>In order to advertise that this network supports OWE the Access
        Point will include the OWE Vendor-specific Information Element in
        Wireless Beacon frames.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    VSA (221)  |    Length (5) |           OUI              
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       OUI (Cont)  |         Type                  |    Sub-type   |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure><list style="hanging">
            <t/>

            <t hangText="VSA">One octet. The IEEE Assigned Vendor-Specific
            Information element ID - 221.</t>

            <t hangText="Length">One octet. The length of the information
            field, including the OUI - 5.</t>

            <t hangText="OUI">Three octets. The OUI for the of the entity that
            has defined the content of the particular vendor-specific
            information element - 64-6A-74 (AUTH-SERVERS). [ If approved, this
            may move under the IANA OUI if desired]</t>

            <t hangText="Type">One octet. OWE has been assigned Type 1 under
            the AUTH-SERVERS OUI</t>

            <t hangText="Sub-type">One octet. Sub-type identified the version
            of the OWE protocol. Currently only 0 is defined.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>An Access Point that includes the OWE Vendor-specific Information
        Element in beacon frames is signalling that is supports OWE on that
        particular SSID, and that they PSK is the same as the SSID. Client
        (STAtions) connecting to OWE enabled networks MUST use the SSID as the
        PSK, and MUST NOT display a "lock" icon in the list of SSIDs when
        scanning. User Interfaces MAY provide some feedback that this is an
        OWE protected network, but this should not be too prominent to avoid
        users assuming that they are getting more security than they actually
        are.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>[ To be completed after discussions ]</t>

      <t>Currently the OWE Vendor-specific Information Element is using type
      1, sub-type 0 under the AUTH-SERVERS OUI. This is to allow
      experimentation with OWE without squatting on the IANA OUI. If OWE
      progresses within the IETF, and the IESG chooses, I'm fine to place this
      under the IANA OUI, or for it to remain under AUTH-SERVERS. It's all
      just numbers.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>There are many attacks that this does not protect against, including
      attackers watching the 4-Way Handshake and deriving the PTK between the
      clinet and the user. This is a weakness in the wireless specification,
      and not specific to OWE. In order to not have the user assume that they
      are getting stronger protection than they really are, the user interface
      should not provide obvious feedback that OWE is in use. OWE simply
      raises the bar slightly, it does not claim to solve all wireless
      issues.</t>

      <t>This solution does not protect against so called "fake AP" attacks.
      Wireless networks that use PSKs that the attacker may know are
      vulnerable to an attacker standing up an access point with the same SSID
      and PSK. This is not specific to OWE, it affects all WiFi networks.</t>

      <t>This solution does not (directly) protect against disassociation
      attacks and the attacker observing the client authentication. This is
      not specific to OWE.</t>

      <t>This solution does not claim to provide "strong" security, it is
      intended to be less insecure than "open" WiFi. In order to avoid users
      assuming that they are getting more security than they really are, OWE
      protected networks do not get a "lock" icon then scanning for WiFi
      networks.</t>

      <t>Ideally users would only associate to networks that they trust, using
      WPA2-Enterprise (802.1X) with certificates that they trust, and then
      immediatly use a VPN to a trusted endpoint. However, open wifi is really
      convenint and users will continute to want it. While abstainance is the
      best policy, OWE recognises that users will continue to behave in risky
      ways, and aims to make this slighly less risky...</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>By making "open" wireless encrypted by default we aim to decrease the
      incidence of passive eavesdropping by pervasive monitors and idle
      attackers.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors wish to thank some folk.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <reference anchor="IEEE.802-11i"
                 target="http://standards.ieee.org/getieee802/download/802.11i-2004.pdf">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Autonomous System (AS) Numbers">IEEE 802 Part 11:
          Wireless LAN Medium Access Control (MAC) and Physical Layer (PHY)
          specifications Amendment 6: Medium Access Control (MAC) Security
          Enhancements</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sidr-iana-objects-03.xml'?>
    </references>

    <section title="Changes / Author Notes.">
      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section before publication ]</t>

      <t>From -00 to -01.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Nothing changed in the template!</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
